all right greetings everyone
welcome to cohort 4 on June 20th for
chapter one discussion
we're going to get to chapter one
discussion in one second but I wanted to
just show one area of development and
something that people can explore
um and then mention one thing about math
learning group so first in the equations
page
there's a few sub pages that might be
interesting to explore
first where we previously had the
equation screenshots so you could like
Mouse over equation 2.1 and click on the
screenshot
um we added the latex so this is just a
plain text code that renders in coda
then there's some sub views that use
Coda AI so this explanations View
these prompts
um basically just to show what it looks
like in code AI explain the latex as if
I'm not familiar how would a high
schooler be interested in this what's
some summary code where is this equation
important and can you explain the
variables it's not perfect but it gets
pretty far very cool
this is the explanations page there's a
philosophy page just one column but it's
just bring up 10 philosophy questions
and a lot of these are like awesome
discussion starting points
you know what what does Divergence mean
all these things and then also languages
so here's just a few languages
but we can add
people's preferred languages just
totally feel free to make a suggestion
we can add more AI columns
um so we have to keep on exploring this
because the latex representation with
plain text is really amenable to this
kind of language model work
so just mention that and then also
um someone in cohort for is interested
in the math learning group I think
they're
[Music]
um
they're potentially interested in like a
morning time UTC
but if somebody else is interested then
we can kind of get this going
so it could be in the Discord
but if anyone is interested to pick up
with math learning group and basically
just it could be an unrecorded session
in the Discord
another hour
um to go over the equations
um
sorry about that um
so if anyone is interested
um maybe just make write a comment here
and just say here sometimes I'd want to
do this just basically like a math study
time
um and then let's just see if there's a
any specific options for what times
people want to do such activities so
on either the AI or the math learning
group does anyone have any just general
thoughts or questions otherwise we'll
move to chapter one
all right
so
let's head over to chapter one
um
just right off the bat before we get to
the
um
questions
it would be awesome if anyone could just
share any of their Reflections on
chapter one just
anything about their experience reading
it or what what they felt it was like or
what stuck with them
or anything that kind of raised after
they
um
read chapter one
um yeah
um so I've had some familiarity with
active inference for a while so a lot of
what I read already tracks for me
um but that said
I'm curious about
variational uh free energy is like a
particular
it seems that so active friends seems to
be based on a particular
form of Bayesian
inference that it relies upon like this
variational
formulation I'm more curious about that
I assume the textbook will get much more
into
what's specific to variational free
energy is as opposed to some other
um formulation of it but yeah that's
something that that I'm kind of still
chewing on right now
thank you
anyone else
Yeah I'd write a chapter one a while ago
and
I think I just Dove deeper into it
knowing that you know we're looking for
questions and stuff but I really
appreciated the um the video that you
and Ollie did so I watched that for the
first time
today and I really appreciated the heads
up to actually read ahead to chapter 10
which I'll do yeah that looks good
um for me in this this more in-depth
reading um action really stuck out to me
um so I went to the ontology to look at
the definition of action
that's like Central to my area I'm in
motor neuroscience
uh
and I can relate to the idea that action
has to have a goal of purpose but I
noted that in the ontology that goal
purpose is not in the definitions
it's more of a general sort of
Behavioral definition
um
and then I started to think about you
know in our area we also use
inaction so like action imagery
and observational learning which you're
not really acting you're watching
somebody else
and and so I posted that question about
um does Action have to change the world
and what do we mean by that do we mean
like I'm going to change the physical
world that we all share
or am I actually sharing my internal uh
changing my internal model
of the world through action
yeah so in summary I really got hung up
on this this action
um terminology
cool that that those are some great
things to explore
anyone else with a just any thought
about chapter one
and
I I'm from I was familiar with the
Bayesian brain hypothesis about like the
you know our mind is kind of uh a
predictive mechanism and
yeah but but like this framework
um you know the more I thought about it
the more I started seeing like these
patterns around me like thinking about
you know the different uh things that I
observe in in that sense of active
inference like uh the action and the
perception
and and like specifically I saw it like
in children's Behavior
for example like uh
you know that the ability to to change
their mind and and the relief
in contrast with like stubbornness
sometimes you know when they're very
stubborn and kind of like a you know
they will do whatever they can to change
their reality although you know they
can't necessarily do so but so it was it
was very interesting just uh thinking
about like uh various behavioral
um patterns that I see around me and
translate them into this framework
thank you
yeah of here and then anyone else uh
question about uh salincy uh because I'm
quite familiar with the definition of
salinity in vision science in which
something is silent if you know the
visual features involved are different
from what you have in your neighbor
but I think that silencio has a much
more general definition in active
inference some quite interesting to
understand you know how it is Quantified
and what the Yeah it's proper definition
you know it's generalization how it
generalize you know the very simple
definition in uh in vision science
yeah
cool uh for me uh I'm a psychiatrist so
um talking about Helen Hall uh Freud who
invented the cycle analytic theory was
influenced by holy molds and as you can
see in the chapter one and also at
chapter two uh Helen Holmes said that
perception is an unconscious inference
process
and which is quite interesting because
um
so the cycle analytic theories are based
on uh the assumption that individuals uh
make really individual uh
interrelationship based on their
childhood memories and experiences and
based on the fact uh I I I got quite
curious about uh whether we can explain
psychoanalytic theories based on active
inference or other computational models
that are based on these assumptions or
theories that are inspired by Helen
holds or other uh
other and other scientists who are also
having similar similar uh points
cool
there's definitely some other
people in the in the textbook group and
around so I hope that they can continue
on this topic anyone else want like a
general
um topic or we can return to some of
these mentioned points as well as some
of the other asked questions
um
just uh I don't want to track too much
but just in response to Young Boon uh I
and maybe you're already familiar with
this but the way I ended up in active
inference uh was through the work of
Mark songs uh and neuropsychoanalysis I
yeah so I I would strongly recommend
checking him out and he he wrote a piece
where he completely wrote rewrites
Freud's uh like early scientific paper
um using the terminology of of active
inference
um I think it's great and I'd be happy
to explore the relationship between
psychoanalysis and active inference like
more potentially within the confines of
of this group in the textbook
oh yeah I I heard about him but uh I
never actually uh read his papers so
I'll look it up thanks thanks for
bringing up
sure
thank you to Daniel
well you want to unmute and go for it or
he I just wanted to mention who worked
North half's work in relation to
um I mean psychoanalytic understanding
of active inference uh it's not
completely in line with Mark Stones line
of research but it provides an
alternative path uh through some of the
uh psychoanalytic ideas of active
inference based on his own spatial
temporal philosophy in Europe
okay cool
all right well let's just revisit some
of these topics and then turn to the
questions but we're totally
just killing and and whichever
um ways that people want to go or anyone
who wants to raise your hand like you
know what
whatever comes to mind let's just
do them while we're here
um
some of these
as with the many coats of paints idea
we're just gonna kind of give like a
first
or a few thoughts on and we're going to
be revisiting in the coming chapters
because like this is the topic chapter
one is just kind of like opening the
door
so let's we're gonna certainly address
all of this once
all these topics are going to come back
like again and again
because the ontology gets Revisited so
much so
um
active inference being based upon the
variational free energy as opposed to
some other formulation
we're going to talk about this a lot
more in chapter two and in equation 2.5
we're going to meet the variational free
energy
and so leading up to equation 2.5 and in
this discussion around 2.5 and in
Chapter 2 and elsewhere
we're going to talk about like what do
we mean by variational free energy and
why is active inference using it
essentially it's a really tractable and
optimizable heuristic
that lets us carry out Bayesian
inference efficiently because there's
situations where if you had infinite
Computing resource you could do exact
Bays you could just plug and chug and
just do the matrix multiplication and
get the exact correct answer
however with large data sets that's not
really tractable and so in Bayesian
statistics and this is even outside and
before active inference people use
variational methods because they're
super effective computationally so for
example a variational autoencoder
a variational autoencoder is a widely
used machine learning method or a
Bayesian statistical method
and a variational autoencoder finds the
optimal fit for data not underfitting or
overfitting
through finding the variational free
energy
so inactive inference a lot of times
there's there's a lot of interpretation
and a lot of extension of what free
energy is in all of this but it's also
possible to kind of pull back to this
pretty non-contentious
Bayesian statistical interpretation
and just
consider variational methods
as being part of Bayesian statistics and
used to tractively optimize challenging
inference problems
so we're going to talk more about that
in chapter two anyone have a thought or
a question on this
um Ali please
I wanted to
point to the distinction between
variation of pre-energy and expected
free energy because
as it says here active in prints is
based upon the variation formulation
it's true but uh
the perceptual part of active inference
theory is based on variation of free
energy but when it comes to action
policy selection and decision making the
parameter to be to be optimized is
actually expected free energy
which is expressed in equation 2.6 so
basically those two equations between
variationally free energy expressed in
equation 2.5 and the expected free
energy expressed in equation 2.6 can be
seen as parallel to each other but uh
they're used to formulate different
aspects of uh for of active inference
one is for perception and the other one
is for action
awesome thank you Ali two ways to
minimize free energy
update your mind through perception and
learning
action through changing the world
the only thing you can't do is like put
your thumb on the scale and directly
change your sensory outcomes so you
prevent the thumb going on the scale
because you don't have a line going from
the internal States out to the sense
States
so that the set states are only coming
in that's inbound dependency
and then that leaves two avenues for
reducing
um free energy perception and action and
we're going to talk a lot more about
this in chapter two when equation 2.5
and 2.6 come into play
okay
continuing on this theme of action
so action was brought up and obviously
like this is one of the really exciting
pieces
this is what is going to be referenced
throughout the book
a unified approach on perception and
action or all these different ways which
we see active inference presented
like going Beyond passive or perceptual
inference
so does Action have to change the world
is this changing the physical
environment or can we change the
generative model through action
thank you um Holly
uh yes so uh maybe I'll just uh yeah
please I think you know I think you know
the when Ali brought up expected free
energy you know you're you're making
changes to your policy your brain uh
your model and
um and so then what's happening is that
and what I find interesting uh is the
leverage points and this concept that
making a very slight change in your
understanding of the world has a much
larger effect than an actual you know
physical action you can see it um there
in that image so I thought and I don't
know if I don't know if a variation of
the energy and the expected for energy
really take that into account that you
know that these you know the The
Leverage points or not that maybe some
people have some ideas
well it's like like in nested modeling
like for a generative model that only
sees up to this point
the optimal leverage Point that's
detected is going to be so and so but
then a deeper generative model might be
able to see uh more leverage points
Ollie
uh well rather than describing action as
something that changes the environment
if we want to talk a bit more precisely
uh what action means in active inference
is actually
one in which active States intervene
constantly in external Dynamics right
and uh formally it means a kind of
Jacobian coupling between the external
states that depend upon the act upon the
act of the states or active intervention
so uh what we mean by changing the
environment uh we mean more precisely
the the kind of active state that would
lead to a kind of causal intervention uh
in the environment and not something
that just
I don't know it changes something per se
and this kind of this station comes into
play when we want to talk about uh
covert and over actions as discussed in
phenomenology which will come to later
in the book but yeah I think that would
be helpful to
awesome you have so many things to look
ahead to overt action is physically
manifested embodied action
covert action or internal action is
attention or mental action
and so that is like something that
doesn't necessarily
um
change outside of the generative model
but it's it's modeled with attention and
action inside the model and there's
actually
um even a very cool
um recent work on transparent and
explainable artificial intelligence and
again just looking ahead
here they use
attention and meta awareness as internal
or covert attention
uh generative models in an artificial
intelligence way but this model was
actually developed in a meditation and
phenomenology setting
where the action selection was internal
attentional control not external control
um
yeah I'll put the um this is the
explainable AI paper in the chat and
then also just again looking ahead one
place to to what is this concept of
action this is figure 4.3 which is kind
of like a Rosetta Stone figure
Pi are going to be the actions that are
selected from
and where those actions intervene is how
the hidden states of the world change
Through Time
so if the hidden States s changing
through time is like the true
temperature in the room
and at each time Point T you have a
thermometer reading that gets emitted
from the true temperature so we're only
able to observe the observables which is
the thermometer readings
and there's the true underlying changes
in temperature or you could think of
this as the true underlying activity of
the neural system and the observation is
the fmri that's kind of where this comes
from in terms of like friston's lineage
with SPM
and then
if there's two actions you can take turn
on the heater or not
it causally intervenes in how States
change their time maybe if you don't
turn on the heater it just passes the
hidden State on forward without changing
it and if you do turn on the heater it
increases it by one per time step
that's that's one sense of um action
and then also just by by mousing over
um we see it from the ontology and also
we we can update the ontology it's it's
never like these things are locked
definitions just to be clear but we see
a really common pattern which is that
there's like a broad and a narrow sense
a lot of these terms in the active
anthontology action belief attention
salience
things that people have brought up today
there's like a broad sense qualitative
definition which largely or exactly is
how we would use this day to day
just action is what occurs
super general term and then there's like
a narrow or a more technical definition
which sometimes conveys how this is
operationalized in generative modeling
so more specifically
actions are the active States
that the agent's generative model
is going to select
and actually and so that's like more of
the quantitative and formal definition
of action
and then we'll explore a lot about how
his action selected
because that is the entire expected free
energy
imperative is the selection of action
and how goal orientation preference
orientation expectation orientation
is embedded Within action
despite there not being a reward
function as we might see in reward
learning reinforcement learning
we're going to have a different approach
for adaptive and flexible Behavior
that's not based upon reward learning or
reward function
okay any any other thoughts or just any
other ideas on on this in action Martin
so does Action have to have movement
it's one thing I'm looking at here I
mean the the overt versus the cover so
overall obviously I have to have some
movement that I could observe
um but he said uh earlier that you could
have the covert like for example
attention
being a covert action
yeah well depending on the system of
Interest action could be an API call so
certainly it doesn't have to be a
person's body that we're modeling could
be a computational or a purely
informational system
um
and then covert or internal attention I
mean you could argue it has some
physical informational substrate
so it's not like it's um you know
happening in some some you know
alternative plane of existence but for
the purposes of the modeling it might
not be realized through a gross
morphological movements
yeah and and it's going to be super cool
like how we're gonna when we look at um
figure 4.3 as kind of this cognitive
kernel or this kind of firmware element
and then again when we take it to uh
when we look at how these
um models compose
even just starting to see familiarity
here in figure two
we see basically this figure 4.3
downward facing e that's the inference
part
hidden State and observations and policy
intervening that's like this
downward facing e
policy intervening
and then that just gets nested
and so that speaks to the composability
of these kinds of Bayesian graphs
and then
in when you look at a specific model it
becomes clear which actions are
associated with overt movement and which
actions are associated with covert
attention
um
okay any other thoughts or thoughts or
questions
um yeah I guess just to briefly kind of
add to the table under
action
um like on page 10 ever so briefly
um the authors make the distinction
between
exploration and exploitation
and um that seems like a really
interesting or useful
division to me like so both of them seem
to be
both of them are related to minimizing
free energy or expected free energy in
this context and
um yeah exploration is to resolve
uncertainty so I view that as like
taking in new information versus
um exploitation which has to do more
with
yeah acting on the World to bring your
your observations into line with
whatever your your goal is uh or your or
your plan is your your set point
to use that the word from cybernetics
yeah
thank you and here's a really clear
claim in contrast with other Frameworks
policy selection so behavioral selection
inactive inference automatically
balances exploration and exploitation
now this is a um
very
strong version of the claim as we'll
explore it's not that simply making an
active inference model does
automatically balance it it's not like
just writing it out is going to make you
know the startup work and the ship work
and the plane fly and all of this so so
it can be read too strongly
it's not that it's automatically going
to be effective however it sets the
stage or it provides an accounting
system
for the the Adaptive finessing between
exploration and exploitation
and
um
we'll explore that more in chapter two
when we look at what is it that expected
free energy and variational free energy
are
and then how is it that that policies
are selected behaviors are selected that
are able to adaptively finesse between
more exploratory behavior when there's
information to learn and more
exploitative behavior when there's kind
of pragmatic value on the table and
maybe it's more important to just get
the pragmatic value rather than to um
continue learning
but that's where we see
um variation in
Behavior ultimately variation in
cognition and behavior when there's too
much attention paid to epistemic or to
pragmatic value
and that's a lot of where like these
like Precision Psychiatry cognitive
modeling things come into play
foreign
[Music]
yeah
any other thoughts or questions on this
it kind of connects to to even the next
point that was on
salience
so
um
salience
again just as it is in the ontology not
the it's the only or the final
definition but it's just the extent to
which a cue is going to be attended to
a cue that is not salient
has no attention to it
and something that's not being attended
to the consequences for the queue are
diminished in the limit case if you
didn't pay attention to something it
just you know
didn't cross your radar it doesn't
update the generative model
that's like attention to zero in The
Other Extreme case when the attention is
super high it's like you're updating
your prior to just whatever it is the
new data point is you perfectly attend
to it and it is like the is same as
having like no memory
so no attention is like
totally pushing your prior forward
full memory
full attention no memory
and then finding out what is an Adaptive
amount of remembering and learning and
forgetting
um
Salient observations are those that
resolve uncertainty
that's the information that we're
seeking out
is the information that reduces our
uncertainty about something
and then how much it reduces it
we're going to talk about some
formalisms especially in chapter two
for comparing like is this sequence of
observations or that sequence of
observations going to be more Salient
which one is going to have higher
epistemic value
which one is going to reduce my
uncertainty more
which one will I learn more by viewing
which one will update my prior is more
which one should I pay attention to more
those are all kind of like related
questions for like which information is
going to be the good information
and these are the the two sides of the
joint imperative
for expected free energy
Information Gain and pragmatic value
epistemic value
how good is the information
pragmatic value what is the utility
am I going to be at homeostasis
exploration exploitation
and so expected free energy is like this
unified imperative
that contains both of those elements
such that different policies can be
ranked or evaluated or upweighted
based upon how well they contribute to
both Information Gain and pragmatic
value
comes up in chapter two but just wanted
to kind of preview it
any other
um thoughts or questions or let's let's
go to the questions table and just like
the the questions that people are most
interested
okay first I'm going to go to the
chapter four or cohort four questions
so just to make sure that even if they
have a few upvotes that that all of your
questions can be addressed so we'll
first look at this question
and then we'll turn to chapter one
questions overall
so as always like you know whenever
you're watching or participating
even if it's a chapter that was long
discussed ago or you know up ahead
just add questions it's it's really
awesome and upvote them so that and
develop the discourse so we can have
good short answers for these
okay
page nine action minimizes free energy
and surprise by changing the world
okay so talked a little bit about that
previously
does this imply that the agent
implements action to alter their world
or their actions implemented to change
the Asians model of the world or both
can an Asian Implement action not solely
to minimize their free energy but free
energy in another agent for example
using action demonstration for
observational learning
yeah does anyone have any thoughts on
this
okay I'm just starting with the
observational learning two two quick
angles listen again everyone can add
more in live stream 53
um sequence
there were some paleoanthropologists
and we discussed observation learning a
lot
and they highlighted how a lot of times
people have focused on the kind of
moment of innovation for example in um
creating stone tools in in human
cultures in history
but it's not just about the one
innovator making the stone tool it's
actually in the moment of observational
learning
when the onlooker
is able to either understand or not
understand and ultimately adopt or not
adopt or to copy or not to copy that
behavior
and so they approached this from an
active inference perspective
and this also brings up ideas like
thinking through other Minds ttom
which is kind of like the active version
of theory of mind
but thinking through other minds or
thinking with other Minds is more
explicitly like
one's generative model
in a social environment
also includes a generative model of what
the other
is thinking and doing
and so
um if if one is in an uncultured setting
where action demonstration can be used
for observational learning then these
are the kinds of dynamics that that are
possible to model so it's one angle is
yes it's been considered in a social and
cultured setting how like gesture and
demonstration and observation might play
a role in transfer learning
um
a more Technical and general response is
in multi-agent systems
you have
agent reducing their own free energy
making their own perception Action Cycle
but also you have like the joint
distribution you know you have the nest
mate going about their own way
but then in the aligned or the
healthiest or adoptive setting the
colony is also reducing its expected
free energy
so One agent or neuron or an Esme or a
person
might undertake an action that increases
their own surprise transiently
as part of a distributed cognitive
system
that has a joint free energy that is
reduced through that action
so it's not necessarily like every
single subunit is always and only
reducing its free energy per se
but the Adaptive whole
is going to reduce its free energy and
that might be
um entailing some subunit increasing its
surprise
uh yes than anyone else
uh yeah I mean I think I'm I keep
thinking in a way as a psychiatrist so
uh it feels like like psychoanalytic
therapy itself is something a therapist
suing Trying to minimize the free energy
of the client
because like they provide explanations
and interpretations about why they are
doing such Behavior or why they are
making such relationships with others so
I guess maybe uh in a broad aspect I
would say uh giving providing
explanations about why some individuals
are behaving in such way would be
another action that actually reduces the
free energy of another agent
that's very cool yeah like by providing
a narrative summary it's a sense making
tool that helps
explain and make sense of their
perceptions and actions Martin
yeah it's really interesting and thanks
for that uh it just got me thinking you
know sometimes we
we I guess we try to free
um minimize energy and others directly
like I'm a university teacher so by
teaching I'm trying to reduce you know
their free energy
um but sometimes you find it's best to
let them
on their own way so I'm just thinking
about like in fact analytics which is
very distant field from my area but uh
letting others interpret meaning from
their situation rather than
bringing it for them if that makes sense
and I'm just thinking you know
maybe this is a side topic but
would active infants speak to what's a
better approach
or want to do it for the other or to let
the other explore
in a way let them work through that
space of energy free energy and then
find their own way to minimize that
yeah great
topics
oh yeah I think that's a really good uh
point because like at in cycle analysis
we sometimes like
um
have to choose whether to give a very
direct interpretation or sometimes we
let the patient to understand what's
going on by themselves but it's always a
controversial
um question about what to do
well we do have some like theories and
some sense about like when what to do on
certain situations but uh it's quite a
Pity that we don't really have like a
very uh scientific grounds for what to
do in psychoanalysis so I think that's a
really good point
let's go to mind is uh this this came up
with this chapter in fact this so if
we're working to minimize our free
energy right and we sort of
acting in a world
to minimize surprise how do we avoid
confirmatory bias
you know so I'm thinking now that the
world is flat so I am going to reinforce
that model because if I don't then
that's going to create some uh free
energy right it's going to create a
surprise so I'm gonna act in the world
I'm going to hang out with people who
don't challenge that and I'm thinking
back into psycho um
Psychiatry practice or counseling maybe
uh
people may have ingrained sort of models
in the perceiving the world just based
on that model
um
resulting confirm it's very bias
yeah this is a is a very important topic
especially as the
as they put it existential imperative is
self-evidencing
to repeatedly re-measure my body at
homeostatic temperature
to be unsurprised about re-measuring
myself at homeostatic temperature
is to maintain homeostasis
so in reward learning you would say well
homeostatic temperatures are the most
rewarding that's the top of the reward
function and then we're going to
basically Hill Climb to get to the most
rewarding body temperature
that's the reward learning paradigm
inactive your preference is your
expectations the C Factor
is what you expect expect to find myself
at body temperature that's the bottom of
the bowl I'd be the least surprised at
37c and I'd get more surprised as I went
out and now we're going to go to the
bottom of the bowl
and we're going to pursue the most
likely course of action bound our
surprise with expected and variational
free energy
and so with the imperative as
self-evidencing and surprisal bounding
we're going to pursue likely Paths of
action
rather than with the imperative being
reward learning the imperative is to
maximize reward
however
does self-evidising mean that we
um
seek out homophily doesn't mean that we
just shut our eyes and go into the dark
room
these are really important topics and
for example in the dark room problem
um it has been discussed for many years
people say well if the imperative of the
generative model is to reduce surprise
then why don't people just go into
sensory deprivation where there's highly
predictable sensory inputs
and this has been discussed and
addressed for for a long time but the
short answer is while you're in the room
reducing your uncertainty about your
visual field
you're increasing your uncertainty about
a variety of other aspects that are
required for operation of the organism
and so you kind of net on balance
uncertainty is rising while you're in
the room
which is why we are always adaptively
moving around and seeking information
and all of this
however you can always set up a
constrained or a toy generative model
that exhibits any given limitation or
pathology
that's not too surprising itself
but to actually use this as an
accounting system for the kinds of
adaptive and interesting behavior that
organisms do exhibit that's the
interesting piece not whether you can
make a
um visual input only generative model
that may select to be in a dark room
but if you have an active visual entity
that can turn on a light
it may turn on the light or if it has a
hunger
uh cue it may need to seek food
eventually so it's a little bit of a
non-sequit or a kind of over
interpretation of a thought experiment
that's just really in a little bit of a
um
partial
way
trying to come at this so
you can imagine that there's situations
where self-evidencing goes right and
where it goes wrong
and that's exactly the space that we're
exploring
a lot of times when I think about
homeostasis and temperature
um I think about you know like huberman
and many uh kind of biohackers want you
to uh you know experience cold contrast
therapy and especially if you are
sensitive to cold you know it's very
important that you get in there and do
your cold plunge your cold showers and
so that's that's I think that's an
interesting example where you're
changing that you know that set point
basically
um by by doing other activities that
seem opposite to what uh you know what
would what would make you comfortable
cool thank you
okay
any other thoughts or questions or let's
look at like one or a few of these asked
questions just just a general question
Daniel so when we post questions because
I posted that one I had to go to the
main table to post a question and then
it feeds into the cohort four is that
how it works I couldn't I couldn't post
directly into there yeah
um all the uh it's it's all
there's only one underlying questions
object
so each of these are like different
views so if you just go here and just
like hit enter
you'll add a new row
and you can ask a question in cohort for
and then that'll be like in chapter one
and in cohort four
um and so that it'll come up when we go
to chapter one questions as well or you
could um
yeah or you could ask and but then it
might not necessarily be tagged to
cohort for
but it doesn't really matter what cohort
it you know as long as it's in the
chapter that's a good place got it
thanks
cool
well
um
one distinction and and you know I look
forward to seeing some of you
um
next week in the other time also
discussing chapter one
um or next week at this time where we'll
be in chapter six with cohort four
you're all welcome to join but a really
key distinction
that's a that's um raised in figure 1.2
is the high road and the low road
and this is basically going to structure
chapters two and three
the low road is going to describe how
the low road is basically Bayesian
statistics
that's how we're going to do cognitive
modeling
but you could use Bayesian statistics to
model anything you could do it on health
records you could do it on weather data
so Bayesian modeling doesn't have to be
about adaptive cybernetic Auto poetic
agents Bayesian statistics the how can
be about anything
chapter two low wrote
chapter 3 is going to be the high road
and the high road is like the kind of
what or why
and it's self-organized
self-evidencing systems
and so this describes more like the
specifications for adaptive agents this
is like what they need to be doing
to be
observed repeatedly
by an observer and or by themselves in
this kind of like sophisticated
reflexive sense
but it doesn't necessarily say how that
happens
it turns out where the why and the how
meet is active inference we're going to
be using Bayesian statistics that's how
to model adaptive cybernetic entities
that's why
and so that's kind of going to be
explored in the chapters two and three
low road High Road
so that's kind of the the
big structuring motif
ultimately of this textbook
um Olivier
yeah in
in the figure there is a an order you
know in all the items on the lower Road
and a high road uh it is although
important to understand anything or just
you know one group and another group
it's a it's a schematic ordering I
believe that there is a way to read them
in order but it's not an exhaustive or a
unique ordering so
um up
so for example
um
oh sorry someone is someone closing the
okay so base theorem is just describing
basically tautological statements about
conditional and Joint probabilities
this gets used in a generative model
which is basically a model that can be
used in a recognition capacity or an A
generative capacity that's the tale of
two densities
in simple settings or passive settings
we're interested in perception as
inference
but once we go into the anticipatory or
the predictive setting we're interested
not just in dealing with incoming
streaming data but basically making
ongoing predictions now casting
the next kind of into the unknown step
that now casting can take is action as
inference because it's not enough to
just deal with incoming streams of data
sometimes you want to take the action to
open the book to find out
that idea of perception and planning as
inference is Unified in the Bayesian
brain and it turns out that variational
Bayesian methods are going to give us
some tractable optimizable approaches
for approximate Bayesian computation
where exact Bays probably doesn't apply
or is really challenging just like we
kind of mentioned earlier
so that gets us to doing variational
Bayesian optimization
on perception and planning as inference
in the Bayesian brain that's active
inference so that's kind of low road
ordering
the high road ordering
is starting with the free energy
principle which is a non-falsifiable
principle just like the principle of
least action in classical mechanics this
is like a principle for informational
systems
and
under this principle are seen as being
in the game of
self-organization via surprise
minimization
you'll continue to find yourself
organized if you're continually
minimizing your surprise about who and
what you are
that is
um supported
or described by
a partitioning conditional independent
structure called a Markov blanket which
we're going to explore
and the markup blanket can be seen as
carrying out self-evidencing through
this kind of anticipatory real-time
predictive processing which is related
to predictive coding
and in the extended embedded inactive
setting that can be understood as
basically self-authoring self-meaning
making and ultimately even extended
Niche Construction
which gets us to active inference from
The High Road
so again not exhaust exhaustive or or
unique ordering but certainly something
that they have considered and laid out a
certain way
thank you everyone
for this awesome
um chapter one discussion
I hope to see you
um
either next week at the other time or
whenever
and just leave a comment on this page
here
if you um want to start up the math
group so thank you all
thank you